<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of Gods omnipotencie and prouidence</title>
            <author>Carter, Bezaleel, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4692A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119930</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20608</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20608)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of Gods omnipotencie and prouidence</title>
                  <author>Carter, Bezaleel, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by C. L[eege] And are to be sold [in London] by Matthevv Law, in Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Foxe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and distribution, and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; A3 and A7 torn affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20608:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20608:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A SERMON OF</hi> Gods Omnipotencie and Prouidence.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL.</hi> 95. 3.</bibl>
               <p>The Lord is a great God, and a great King aboue all gods.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by C. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And are to be ſold by <hi>Matthew Law,</hi> in Pauls Churchyard at the ſigne of the Foxe. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20608:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20608:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, It may ſeeme meere preſumption, and vain oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for one of my yeeres to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo vnworthy labours to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, especially when ſo many aged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>end Diuines, of excellent learning, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nd iudgement, and continued experience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſilent in this kinde. My apologie for my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is, the common plea, I meane importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of freinds, and for mine owne part, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not in conſcience deny ſo religious a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of my Chriſtian auditors. God that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>es the ſecrets of all hearts knows it, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſelfe loue, were neuer the ſpurres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>cke mee on to this bolde attempt: onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath beene the height of my deſires, the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of Sion, the benefit of Gods Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> people: if therefore thou repeaſt any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from theſe my paynes, I haue attained to the toppe of my wiſhes. Howſoeuer, here I preſent them to thy fauourable cenſure. In the mean time, I commend both thee and thy grouth in grace, to the helpe and furtherance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Almightie God. <hi>Canham.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Christ Ieſus, BEZALEEL CARTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20608:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20608:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>SERMON OF</hi> Gods power and <hi>providence.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 135. 6.</bibl>
               <q>Whatſoeuer pleaſed the Lord, that did hee in heauen, in the earth, in the ſea, and in all deepes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, Worſh. and Welbeloued,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Scripture is infinitely large <note place="margin">The Lord omnipotent for foure reaſons.</note> in ſetting forth vnto vs the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God: I know, ſaith Dauid, in the verſe foregoing, that the Lord is great, and that our Lord is aboue all Gods. 1. The Lord is mightie, for hee does whatſoeuer hee pleaſes. Gen. 18.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20608:4"/> 14. 2. Hee is mightie, becauſe he works by no meanes. Iob. 26. 2. 3. Pſal. 148. 5. 3. Hee is mightie, for hee workes by weake meanes, Exod. 8. 6. Acts. 12. 25. Laſtly, hee is mightie, becauſe he can doe more then euer hee did from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or will doe to the worlds end. Mat. 26. 52. Now his power in doing whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he pleaſes, is laid down to vs in this text: <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſed the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> At this time I reſolue to reade it in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe, <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſes the Lord, that doth hee, &amp;c.</hi> and I hope I ſhall offer no violence to my text, for God is one and ſame, God yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for euer, his arme is not ſhortened, nor his power diminiſhed, it hath beene alike from the beginning, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue alike, till time ſhall be no more, <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſes the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for my method, take it thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I will ſhew you that God doth what he pleaſeth. 1. In heauen. 2. In the earth. <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 3. In the ſeas. 4. In all deepes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I will come to vſe and application.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>1. <hi>In heauen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>By heauen, I vnderſtand whatſoeuer is aboue the earth: Paul I remember makes <note place="margin">1. Particular.</note>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20608:4"/> mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of three heauens, a firſt, a ſecond, &amp; a third heauens; like Noahs Arke that was contriued with a firſt, ſecond, and third roome.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt, reaches from the earth to the moone.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, from the moone to the third heauen, which by the learned is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>coelum empyreium,</hi> comprehending the ſeauen planets, &amp; the firmament, which is the receptacle of all the fixed ſtarres.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And the laſt, is that which <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the higheſt heauens, the Paradiſe of god, and the ſeate of the bleſſed.</p>
               <p>I might take occaſion to ſhew you that God doth what hee pleaſes. 1. In the firſt heauens. 2. In the ſecond heauens. 3. In the third heauens.</p>
               <p>But leaſt I ſhould ſeeme rather curious then profitable, I will handle this point generally, that God doth what he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in heauen. The heauen is the Lords throne, 1. King. 8. 27. the Angels at his command, as diligent as the ſeruants of the Centurion, Matth. 8. 9. if hee ſaith to one, goe, he goeth; to another, come, he comes; to a third, doe this, he doth it: If to deſtroy Sodome, readie to deſtroy:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20608:5"/> if to preſerue Lot, they can doe nothing, til Lot be come out of Sodom. Knoweſt thou not, ſaid Chriſt, to him that ſmot off the high Prieſts ſeruants ear, that I could pray to my father, and hee would giue me more then twelue legions of Angels? Matth. 26. The ſunne, and the moone, and the ſtarres, the orbs and arches of heauen, obey his voyce: hee cauſed the ſunne and moone to ſtand ſtil till Ioſhua preuailed ouer his enemies, Ioſh. 10. 13. and the ſtarres from heauen to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Siſera, Iudg. 5. 20. Hee commands the winds and ſtorms, and the winds and ſtormes obey him, Mark. 4. 36. The thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and they are obedient to him: Hee ſent thunder to plague the hard hearted Egyptians, Exod. 9. 23. Hee ſent thunder at the prayer of Samuel, 1. Sam. 12. 18. The winds were his ſeruants to bring in quayles to the Iſraelites, Numb. 11. 31. And when Ionah fled from the preſence of the Lord to Tarſhiſh, he rayſed vp a mighty tempeſt, Ion. 1. 4. The ſwift and ſpeedie lightnings are his attendants. When he came to deliuer the law to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, he came in a terrible manner with lightnings, Exod. 19, 16. Hee couereth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20608:5"/> the heauens with clouds, and prepareth raine, Pſal. 147. 8. In the time of Noah the Lord opens the windows of heauen, and commanded the clouds to raine, and then the earth was couered with water, Gen. 7. 19. Againe, he commanded that it ſhould not raine for the ſpace of three yeers and vpwards, in the time of Eliah, 1. King. 17. 1. and then the windowes of heauen were ſhut vp, and the riuers were dried vp, 1. kin. 17. 7. He giues ſnow like wooll, &amp; ſcattereth the hoare froſt aſhes. Pſal. 147. 16. Hee tames the birds of the ayre, euen the wilde rauens: the wild ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens fed the Prophet Eliiah, 1. Kin. 17. 6. In a word, all things in heauen obey him, the Angels, the Sunne, the moone, the ſtarres, ſtormes, tempeſts, thunders, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, raine, ſnow, hayle. Hee giues by his voyce, the multitude of waters in the heauens, hee cauſes his clouds to aſcend from the ends of the earth, hee turnes his lightnings to raine, and brings forth the wind out of his treaſure, Ierem. 10. 13. <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſeth the Lord, that doth hee in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>In the earth.</head>
               <p>As he ruleth all things in heauen, ſo he <note place="margin">2. Particul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20608:6"/> ruleth all things in earth, mooueable and immooueable, man and beaſt: hee ruleth all men, yea the very ſteppes of a man are ruled by the Lord, Prou. 20. 24. he faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the heart of euery man, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands their works, Pſal. 33. 15. by him Kings reigne, and Princes decree iuſtice; by him Princes rule, and all the Iudges and Nobles of the earth, Prou. 8. 15. It is hee that giueth deliuerance vnto Kings, and reſcueth his ſeruants from the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſword, Pſal. 144. 10. he pulleth down Princes, and raiſeth vp Princes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pleaſure. He chaſed the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, Exod. 34. 11. he fought for Iſrael, Ioſ. 10. 42. he gaue Hezekiah victorie, 2. King. 19. 34. hee giues the victorie, he giues the ouerthrow; in a word, he rules all men, the mightie of the earth, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and Kings: The heart of the King is in the hand of the Lord, Prou. 21. 1. and not only ſo, but whatſoeuer is in the earth beſides, with life or without life, * e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>attel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 8. 8.</note> from the lion to the creeping thing: he cauſed a lyon to deſtroy the diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent prophet, 1. King. 13. 24. ſo he gaue Samſon victory ouer a lyon, Iudg. 14. 12 and likewiſe Dauid victory ouer a lyon,
<pb facs="tcp:20608:6"/> 1. Sam. 17. 34. He ſent two be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy the fortie two children that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked the Prophet Eliſha, 2. King. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Frogs, flies, lice, and graſhoppers are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lords mightie armie: he ſpake the word and they muſtred themſelues vp againſt Pharaoh, and made war againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Egyptians, Exod. 8. 5. 9. 1. 10. 28. The wormes likewiſe obey the voice of God: he ſent a worme to deſtroy Ionah his gourd, Ion. 4. 7. and ſo doe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, for he ſent fierie ſerpents amongſt the children of Iſrael, that ſtang them ſo as many died, Numb. 21. 6. The Lord is he that cauſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> trees of the earth to flouriſh, euen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cedars of Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and the tree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> earth to wither, like the wild figg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 21. 19. he raiſed vp a wild gourd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> comfort Ionah, and the next morning he cauſed it to die away, Ion. 4. 7. Hee cauſeth the earth to bring forth the bud of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he herb, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſeede according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his kind, Gen. 1. 11. he, I ſay, ruleth the earth, men, beaſts, trees, plants. The earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the round world, and they that dwel therein, Pſal. 24. 1. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer pleaſeth the Lord, that doth hee in</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20608:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>In the ſeas.</head>
               <p>Thirdly, God doth that which hee pleaſeth in the ſea: The ſea is his, and he made it, and his hands prepared the drie land, Pſal. 95. 5. he diuided the red ſea, ſo as the Iſraelites paſſed through vpon dry land, Exo. 14. 23. He commands the ſea, yea the fiſhes of the ſea are commanded of God from the greateſt to the leaſt: He cauſed a whale to ſwallow vp Ionah, and the ſame whale to caſt him vp againe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the drie land, Ion. 2. 10. and when Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon had gone a fiſhing all night, and could catch nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at length Chriſt cauſed him to lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the deepe, and then he encloaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ole multitude of fiſhes, Luk. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, ſaith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, ruleſt the raging of the ſea, when the waues thereof ariſe, thou ſtilleſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Pſa. 89. 9. his wayes in the ſea, and his pathes in the great waters, and his footſteps are not knowne, Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 77. 19. When Iſrael came out of Egypt, and the houſe of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob from the barbarous people, the ſea ſaw it and fled, Iordan was turned back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Pſalm. 117. Thou haſt, faith the Pſalmiſt, placed the earth vpon her foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20608:7"/> thou couereſt it with the deepe as with a garment: the waters would ſtand aboue the mountaines, but at thy rebuke they flie, Pſal. 104. 5. as if he had ſaid, If thou, O God, didſt not curbe in and bridle the raging of the ſea, it were impoſſible but that the whole world ſhould be ouerwhelmed with water, the waters would ſtand aboue the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, but at thy rebuke they flie: and Pſal. 33. 7. He gathereth the waters of the ſea toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as vpon an heape, and layeth vp the deepes in his treaſure: and yet in another Pſalme, The voice of God is vpon the waters, he fittes vpon the floods, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines king for euer and euer, Pſal. 29. 10. <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſes the Lord, that doth he in heauen, in the earth, and in the ſea.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>And in all deepes.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in the deepes of the ſea: and thus <note place="margin">4. Particular</note> he deliuered Ionah beeing incompaſſed with the deepes, Ion. 1. 2. hee makes the deepes to boile like a pot, Iob. 41. 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in the deepes of the earth: The graue is naked before him, Iob 26. 6. There is nothing hidden, no not in the bottome of the earth, but he ſeeth it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, in the deepe of all deepes: in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20608:8"/> the bottomleſſe pit, Reu. 20. his power is deeper then hel, Iob 11. 8. hell and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction are before the Lord, Pro. 15. 11.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. But the meaning of the place is this, God ruleth not only the ſeas and ſalt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but all freſh riuers, ponds, and lakes, euen the deepes that ſpring out of the vallies and mountaines, Deu. 8. 7. Oh God, ſaith Dauid, Let not the wicked haue their deſire: Oh caſt them into the deepe pits that they riſe not. Pſal. 104. 10 Hee claue the rockes in the wilderneſſe, and gaue the children of Iſrael drinke as out of the great deepes. Pſal. 78. 15. Hee ſpake the word, and the fountaines of the great deepe were broken vp. Gen. 8. 11. The riuers of Egypt hee turned into blood, Exod. 7. 17. and cauſed the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent riuer, the riuer Kiſhon to ſweepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Siſera with his mightie hoaſt. Iudg. 5. 21. Hee turnes the floodes into a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and ſprings of water into dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: againe, he turnes the wilderneſſe into pooles of water, and the drie land into water ſprings, Pſal. 107. 33. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer pleaſes the Lord, that doth hee in heauen, in earth, in the ſea, and in all deepes.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20608:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer pleaſes the Lord that he doth,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this doctrine.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet this muſt be vnderſtood with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation: for ſom things there are which God cannot doe. God cannot lie, Tit. 1. 2. God cannot deceiue, God cannot ſin, God cannot deny himſelfe, &amp;c. here then ariſes the difficulty, how can it be ſaid, that God doth whatſoeuer hee pleaſes, ſince you haue named particulars, that he cannot effect nor bring to paſſe? God cannot ſinne, God cannot cauſe that which is done to be vndone, &amp;c. and therfore God is not omnipotent, neither doth hee whatſoeuer hee wills. But the anſwer is eaſie: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, God doth whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hee pleaſes, but to ſinne, to lie, &amp;c. theſe are not pleaſing to his Maieſtie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, theſe are <hi>opera non potentiae ſed impotentiae,</hi> to ſinne, to die, &amp;c. theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from weakneſſe and infirmitie, and therefore if God were ſubiect to theſe, he were not Almightie: for to ſinne is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of imperfection, yea of ſlauery: know you not ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> that his ſeruants you are whom you obey. Ioh. 8. 34. If God could be ouercome by ſinne, hee ſhould be the ſeruant of ſinne, and if hee could ſubiect himſelfe to the bondage, and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20608:9"/> and ſeruice, and dominion of ſinne, and be vanquiſhed and ouercome by it, hee were not Almighty: for this would derogate from his omnipotency, becauſe it implies a contradiction, to be omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and yet to yeeld to the conqueſt of ſinne: and therefore here rather appeares the mighty power of God, that hee is not ſubiect to theſe infirmities, it is the great power of God, that hee cannot lie, and ſo for ſinne in generall, therefore it is not in God, becauſe he is Almighty and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent. But I leaue the doctrines, and haſten to the vſe. I will firſt deliuer one vſe in generall, and ſo wee will come to more particular application.</p>
               <p>Since God rules all things in heauen, <note place="margin">The generall vſe.</note> and earth, &amp;c. therefore nothing comes to paſſe, without his ſpeciall notice and prouidence, nothing comes by accident, nor nothing comes by chance. The lot is caſt into the lappe, but the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is of the Lord, Prou. 16. 33. who ſaith a thing comes to paſſe, &amp; the Lord hath not done it? out of the mouth of the moſt High proceeds euil and good, Lam. 3. 37. The Lord ſaueth man and beaſt, Pſal. 36. 6. God careth for the birds of heauen and feeds them, Matth. 6. 26. and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20608:9"/> hee numbers our hayres, Matth. 10. 30. Nay, takes notice of euery teare that is ſhedde by the faithfull, and puts them in a bottell, Pſal. 56. 8. Nay, his prouidence extends to the lilies of the field, and to the birds of heauen, euen to the little ſparrow. The Lord giueth, and the Lord taketh away, as it pleaſeth the Lord, ſo come things to paſſe, Iob. 1. 21. Indeede ordinarily we aſcribe whatſoeuer betides vs, to fortune, and chance, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the ſtarres, as if God were not the diſpoſer and ruler of all his workes: there can be no euill in the citie, ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> but the Lord hath done it, Amos. 3. 6. plagues come from God, puniſhments from God, croſſes from God: the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man imputeth his loſſes to fortune, his encreaſe to fortune, &amp; generally vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely deaths, burnings, blaſtings, &amp;c. theſe are imputed to accident &amp; chance, when indeed ſinne is the cauſe, and God is the author of puniſhment. Man ſuffers for ſinne, Lam. 3. 39. our ſinnes are the cables, and cartropes, that hurries down Gods vengeance vpon vs. I kill, ſaith God, and I giue life, I wound and I make whole, Deut. 32. 39. I forme the light, I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20608:10"/> create darkeneſſe, I make peace, and I create euill, I the Lord doe all theſe things, Iſai. 45. 7. This in generall.</p>
               <p>Now in particular this doctrine may ſerue, Firſt for terror to the wicked. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for comfort to the elect.</p>
               <p>Terror to the wicked. 1. In regard of this life. 2. In regard of a better life.</p>
               <p>Conſolation to the elect. 1. for this life. 2. for a better life.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> How can a wicked and a godleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon harbour any quiet in his breaſt, ſince God rules in all places? how can they promiſe themſelues any ſafety, ſince God doth whatſoeuer hee pleaſeth in heauen, in the earth, in the ſea, and in all deepes? how can they promiſe peace to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, when the Lord of heauen is able to muſter vp al his heauenly powers, and ſet legions of heauenly and celeſtiall ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in battell array againſt them? nay how can they euer thinke to be ſaued, ſince God is the Lord of the heauens, that excludeth and admitteth whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he pleaſes? how can they thinke to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vpon the earth, or to be ſafe vpon the ſea, ſince God rules in both theſe; when his power reaches higher then the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb facs="tcp:20608:10"/> deeper then hell, ſince the meaſure of it is longer then the earth, and broader then the ſea, Iob. 11. 8. If they looke vp to heauen, the mighty God of heauen their enemy, Chriſt their enemie, archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Angels, the orbs and arches of heauen, the ſtarres and the planets, all things in heauen ready at Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to bandy againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nay the gates of heauen bard vp againſt them, as it was againſt the fiue fooliſh virgins, Math. 25. 12. If they looke downe to the earth, the earth is weary of bearing ſo vile a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: if they flie to the ſea, that ſwells and rages againſt them: if they flie to the Eaſt, God is there, if to the Weſt God is there, if to the North hee workes in the North, if to the South hee hides himſelfe in the South, Iob. 23. 8. So as the eſtate of a wicked man, is like the eſtate of him that the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeakes of, that flew from a lion, and a bare met him, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> 5. 19. Or like <hi>Plinies</hi> flying fiſh, which beeing in the ſea, is chaſed by the fiſhes, and flying into the ayre is purſued by the birds, which way ſoeuer they go they runne headlong to their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if they take the wings of the morning
<pb facs="tcp:20608:11"/> and flie to the ſea, God commands the ſea, and that makes warre againſt them, as it did againſt the Egyptians, Exod. 14. 28. If they returne to the earth, the earth ſhal be curſed to them as it was to Cain, Gen. 4. 12. If they looke vp to heauen, they flie from a lion to a beare, God like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ready to execute vengeance vpon them for their wicked courſes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truly ſaid the Deuil to Saul, Doeſt thou aske counſell of mee, and God is thine enemy? 1. Sam. 28. 16. It is vaine to conſult or aske counſell, if God oppoſes, if God takes in againſt vs, it is a vaine thing to truſt in charrets or horſes: woe to the rebellious children, ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that ſtrengthen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the ſtrength of Pharaoh, and truſt in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Egypt: for the ſtrength of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh ſhall be their ſhame, and the truſt in the ſhadow of Egypt their confuſion, Iſai. 30. 1. 2. Though hand ioyne in hand, ſaith Dauid, nation ioyne with nation, kingdome with kingdoms, though hand ioyne in hand, yet ſhall not the wicked eſcape vnpuniſhed: I kil, ſaith God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any that can deliuer out of my hands, Deu. 32. 39. Though they dig
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20608:11"/> downe to hell, thence ſhall mine hand take them, though they climbe vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, thence I will bring them downe: though they hide themſelues in the top of Carmel, I will ſearch and take them thence, and though they be hidden in the bottome of the ſea, I will command the ſerpent and he ſhall bite them, Amos 9. 2. 3. This then is the eſtate of a wicked man, but I purpoſe to handle this point more particularly.</p>
               <p>Firſt, God doth what hee pleaſeth in <note place="margin">In heauen.</note> the heauen, and therefore in what a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, in an vncertaine, and ſlipperie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is euery wicked perſon, that ſtands not in good grace &amp; tearmes with God, but ſtands in the eſtate of rebellion, and is out of his fauour, which way ſoeuer hee turnes, encompaſſed about with as many enemies as God hath creatures. For euen as Princes out of their abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie leauie vp forces, in the court, in the citie, in the countrie, amongſt their ſubiects ſuperiour and inferiour: So I ſay the Lord hath, as the earth and ſea at his command, ſo likewiſe all his celeſtiall courtiers the Angels, as it were his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, whereof one is able to ouerthrow an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20608:12"/> hundred foureſcore and fiue thouſand, 2. King. 19. 39. and as he hath his no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, ſo hath hee his inferiour officers, the ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, the moone, all the planets and ſtarres, whereby he can and doth aſtoniſh and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze wicked and godleſſe and rebellious people. He binds the waters in the cloud, and the cloud is not broken vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The pillers of heauen tremble and quake at his reproofe, hee hath garniſhed the heauens, &amp; framed the crooked ſerpent, Iob. 26. 11. 12. 13. Hee commands the ſunne, and it riſeth not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cloſes vp the ſtarres as vnder a ſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, hee maketh the ſtarres Arcturus, Pleyades, &amp; Orion, and the ſtarres of the South, Iob. 9. 7. 8. 9. He commaunds the pillars of heauen, the ſphear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and conſtellations, the planets and ſtarres, Arcturus, Pleyades, and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all theſe are readie to obey the voyce of God, and if hee pleaſe to commaund them to plague the vngodly: and there is not the leaſt of the Lords army, not the leaſt Angel, ſtarre, not the leaſt meteor, but is able, if God but ſpeake the word to deſtroy, I ſay not an Egypt, an Aſia, or a world, but ten thouſand worlds. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a wonder that any wicked man
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20608:12"/> ſhould dare to ſleep vpon his bedde, that they ſhould giue ſleepe to their eyes, or number to their eyelidds, Prov. 6. 4. bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo infinitly beſet with millions of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emies: how miſerably was the poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Eliſha affrighted, when hee ſaw that an hoaſt of men had incompaſſed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and cried out to Eliſha, alaſſe maſter what ſhall we do? 2. king. 6. 15. And how feareful were the children of Iſrael when they departed Egypt, and were purſued by their enemies, they were ſore afraid ſaith the text and cried to the Lord, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 14. 10. A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo I ſay it is a wonder of wonders, that men ſhould be ſo ſecure, that they ſhould not tremble euen as Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar trembled, when hee ſaw the hand writing vpon the playſter of the wall, Dan. 5. 5. that their hearts ſhould not faile them, that diſmaiednes and fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould not ſwallowe them vp: When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mies, not of Egyptians, but Angels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſue them, nay when as all things created from the earth, to circumference of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the lion &amp; the beare, the great beare &amp; the leſſer beare, the crooked ſerpent, Pleyades, and Orion: all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly hoaſt, bidde them battell, and ſet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20608:13"/> themſelues continually in battell array a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, how can they thinke to be <note place="margin">In earth.</note> ſafe vpon the earth, or to proſper vpon the earth, ſince God is the ruler of the earth; methinkes euerie vngodly wretch ſhould bee of Cains minde, that feared leaſt euery man hee met with, were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for his executioner, Gen. 4. 14. May they not iuſtly feare that the earth will take part with her Lord and maker, and ſwallowe them vp, as it did Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, Numb. 16. 1, 2, 3. yea, that the leaſt worme and creeping thing ſhould be made ſtrong enough to deſtroy them: thus proud Herod was worried with wormes, Act. 12. 23. and ſo we reade in Ioel, that the Lord plagued the nation of the Iewes with moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible creatures, graſhoppers, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerwormes, catterpillars, and palmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes, Ioel 2. 25. Pope Adrian was ſlaine by a gnat, others with the ſtone of a raiſon, ſome with an hair in their broth, ſome one way, ſome an other, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes then that euery vile perſon, ſhould feare the vileſt and baſeſt of Gods creatures, euen frogs, flies, and lice, leaſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20608:13"/> theſe ſhould be appointed for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that they ſhould feare to walk in the aire for feare of infection, or yet to remaine in their houſes, for feare leaſt their houſes ſhould reuenge Gods quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell vpon them: may they not feare that euery morſell they eate ſhould bee their bane, and euery droppe of liquor they drinke ſhould be their poyſon? but what ſaith Salomon, Sentence againſt euill is deferred, and therefore the heart is fully bent to doe wickedly, Eccleſ. 8. 11. God doth not open the ſluces and floodgates of heauen vpon vs as he did vpon the old world, Gen. 7. 17. the earth doth not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen her mouth to deuoure, as in the time of Moſes, Numb. 16. 1. God raineth not downe vpon vs fire and brimſtone, as he did vpon Sodom and Gomorrah, Gen. 19. 24. We ſee many an old ſinner, many an olde adulterer, many an old ſwearer, many an old drunkard, and therefore men draw on ſinne with cords of vanitie, Iſa. 5. 18. and commit all manner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with all greedineſſe; theſe let them know (though God bee patient waiting for their conuerſion) yet as he is patient, ſo he is iuſt, and therefore though he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20608:14"/> long (as he is ſlow to anger, Exo. 34. 6.) yet euen as a ſtreame beeing ſtopt carries all before it, or as wet wood being once kindled burns the faſter; ſo though his wrath hath beene a long time kept in with the floodgates of his mercy, yet in the ende his furie ſhall breake out, like a violent ſtreame, to the vtter deſtruction of the wicked. Long did hee beare with the olde world, long did his ſpirit ſtriue with man, Gen. 6. 3. but in the ende hee turned the whole world into an Ocean, Gen. 7. 17. long did he ſtriue with Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, but at length, ſhe was made a prey to the teeth of her enemies, Pſal. 124. 6. &amp; not one ſtone left vpon another: long may the Lord beare with the wicked, but as ſure as God is iuſt, ſo aſſuredly in the ende his wrath and iealouſie ſhall ſmoake againſt them, Deut. 19. 20. how then can they ſooth vp themſelues, and fleſh vp themſelues in their ſinnes? how can they think to be ſafe vpon the earth, ſince the righteous Iudge of the whole world, Gen. 18. 25. is Lord ouer the earth? or how can they think to thriue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper vpon the earth, ſince the earth is the Lords, and the plentie of the earth? Pſal.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20608:14"/> 24. 1. Gold is mine, ſaith God, and ſiluer is mine, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes, Hag 2. 9. Except the Lord builds the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it; except the Lord keepeth the city, the keeper watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in vaine, Pſal. 127. 1. what a madnes is this in a beſotted worldling, to carke and to care, and to digge, and ditch, and delue, and beat his braines, and riſe early, and goe to bed late, Pſal. 127. 2. as if they would command the earth in deſpight of heauen? I tel thee whoſoeuer thou art, if God but command, the heauens aboue ſhall be as yron, and the earth as hard as braſſe, your land ſhall not giue her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, nor your trees their fruit, Leu. 26 19. and therefore ceaſe from your immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate labour, and ſue for Gods bleſſing, for without it you ſow much, but bring in but little, and put all your earnings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a broken bagge, Hag. 1. 4.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, how can a reprobate thinke <note place="margin">In the ſea.</note> to bee ſafe vpon the ſea, ſince God like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe rules the ſeas. I remember what I read of Ionah: When Ionah fled from the preſence of the Lord to Tarſhiſh, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke him to the ſea, Ion. 1. 3. but as ſoon as euer God gaue commiſſion to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20608:15"/> the winds broke forth, and made warre vpon Ionah, Ion. 1. 4. the waters encountered with the winds, and made warre vpon Ionah: nay the fiſh, the whale opened his mouth, and lay wayting to deuoure Ionah, the marriners that were to land him ſafely in Tarſhiſh, conſpired to caſt him into the ſea: nay, if God but ſet againſt vs, then ſhall we euen like Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſet againſt our ſelues, Mat. 27. 5. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah did not in this extremitie plead for, but againſt himſelfe; Take me, ſaith he, and caſt me into the ſea, and ſo ſhall the ſea be calme vnto you, Ion. 1. 12. &amp; how can wicked perſons hope for the leaſt ſafetie vpon the ſea: if the Lord but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſtormes and winds, they obey him, and theſe ſhall worke their ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw; if hee but command, the ſea, the ſhip, the pirats vpon the ſea, the rocks, theſe ſhall worke their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe that neither heauen, nor earth, nor ſea ſets againſt them, yet hath <note place="margin">In the deeps</note> the Lord an other army, and when hee armes himſelfe to vengeance, euen the ſweet waters, and delightfull ſprings ſhal runne vpon the world as it were with drawne ſwords: and hath not the Lord
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20608:15"/> infinitely fought againſt vs with his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie armie, witnes our late floods and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations, breaking downe banks, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng away mils, bridges, &amp;c. the Lord ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med theſe freſh water ſoldiers with ſuch ſtrength and power, that nothing was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſiſt them: and therefore ſtill ſee the miſerable eſtate of an vnſanctified man, if hee eſcapes one euill he meeteth with an other, if he eſcape a firſt, he mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with a ſecond, for the Lords quiuer is full of arrowes, and his thunderbolts are neuer ſpent, if neither heauen, nor earth, nor ſea, yet ſhal the deepes reuenge Gods quarrell vpon them: euen thus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable are they in this life, euen as Ionah in the whales belly was compaſſed with waters, ſo are theſe with enemies aboue, beneath, and round about them.</p>
               <p>And yet behold, this is but their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <note place="margin">The 2. vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the 1. part f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> terror to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wicked.</note> eſtate in regard of this world: ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine their miſerable eſtate in regard of a better life. Is it poſſible that an vnclean perſon ſhould euer thinke to dwell with God, ſo long as God rules in heauen? conſider this point in the name of God, and let it be a doctrine to worke terrour and amazement in vs. God hath ſaid it in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20608:16"/> his word, that neither buggerers, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, nor adulterers ſhal inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, Eph. 5. 5. God that hath the keyes of heauen, and hath the keyes of hell, this God hath ſpoken it, and how canſt thou then that runneſt to the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots houſe, and makeſt thy ſelfe a ſlaue to vncleanneſſe, how canſt thou euer thinke to dwell with God, that euer ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred vncleanneſſe: and ſo for couetous perſons, that forſake the kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, to ſurfet vpon filthie Mammon, how can they ouer thinke to dwell with that God that euer abhorred couetous perſons, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious perſons, drunkards, ſwearers, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars? how can they euer hope to dwel with that God, that abhors malice, abhors ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, abhors ſwearers, and liars? how can ſuch deuilliſh and damned perſons euer thinke to bee ſaued, ſince the heauen of heauens is the Lords? Deut. 10. 14. God he is holy, God he is righteous, God he is pure: how canſt thou then, thou that art vnholy, thou that art vnpure, thou that art vnrighteous, how canſt thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer think to ſet thy foot within the gates of the new Ieruſalem? a ſtinking carkaſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20608:16"/> ſtinkes not more vilely in the noſtrils of man, then an abhominable ſinner ſtinkes odiouſly in the noſtrils of God. Let all ſinnefull wretches know this, that God is their mortall enemie, hee will wound the head of his enemies, &amp; execute ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon his enemies, Deut. 32. 41. we loath not a toad nor a ſcorpion worſe then the Lord hateth them; we hate not the deuill, nor the deuill hateth not man worſe then God hateth them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore queſtionles the Lord will neuer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them into his holy kingdome, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther couetous earth-wormes, beaſtly dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kards, helliſh blaſphemers, extorting vſurers, God will neuer receiue theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſacred preſence, but ſhal ſend them packing with the wicked and the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate into euerlaſting damnation: whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer worketh abomination and lyes, ſhal haue no part in the kingdome of heauen, Reu. 21. 27. the frogs of Egypt ſtanke not more rankely in the Egyptians noſes, Ex. 8. 14. then theſe ſmell rankely in Gods noſthrils: and therefore I ſay, God will ſtop his noſe againſt them, and giue them their portion with hypocrites. All the fearefull, all the vnbeleeuing, and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20608:17"/> murderers, whoremongers, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, idolaters, and liars ſhall haue their part in the lake that burnes with fire and brimſtone, Reu. 21. 8. And therefore now <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the vſe in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> to drawe to a concluſion, as Peter ſaith, humble your ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God, 1. Pet. 5. 6. ſo ſay I, humble your ſelues vnder the mightie hand of God: God he is a mighty God, able to worke your ruine vpon earth, and to caſt both bodie and ſoule into hel fire: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelues therfore before the thron of his grace; for it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God. Thou drunkard that deſtroieſt the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and the good creatures of God by thine intemperancy, and runneſt into all manner of enormities, that thy drunken humour hurries thee into, that makeſt ſtreets and townes ring of thine vnrulines, thou that art mighty to drinke wine and ſtrong drinke, how dareſt thou riſe early, and goe to bed late, to follow drunkennes, ſince God hath denounced a woe againſt drunkards? Iſa. 5. 11. and that God that hath denounced a woe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, is able to caſt both body and ſoule into hell fire.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20608:17"/>
               <p> Thou couetous earthworme, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt a god of thy goods, that diggeſt downe to hell for riches, and eateſt the poore as men eat bread, that art choaked with the loue of the world: thou greedie catterpiller, how dareſt thou continue in this ſinne, ſince God hath ſaid it, That neither theeues, nor railers, nor couetous perſons, ſhall inherite the kingdome of God? 1. Cor. 6. 10. and this God is able to caſt both bodie and ſoule into hell fire.</p>
               <p>Thou blaſphemer of the name of God, that renteſt and teareſt the name of God in peices, and ſpeweſt forth blacke, and feareful, and damnable oaths, and makeſt ſwearing, and curſing, and deuilliſh ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, thy beſt language: how dareſt thou take the name of the Lord in vaine, ſince God hath ſaid it, that he wil not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine? Exod. 20. 7. and this God is able to caſt both bodie and ſoule into hel fire. Dares a ſonne offend his father? durſt Pilate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Caeſar, Ioh. 19. 13. dares the borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer offend the lender? no man will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly offend him that is able to worke him an inconuenience; and thinke wee then that it is a ſafe thing to offend the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20608:18"/> liuing Lord of heauen and earth, that is able doubly and redoubly, and trebly to requite vs, and to render vengeance to thoſe that know him not. If you wil not be reformed, ſaith the Lord to the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Iewes, but walke ſtubbornly againſt me, then will I alſo walke ſtubbornely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and I wil ſmite you yet ſeuen times for your ſinnes, Leuit. 26. 24. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what I read in the 2. Sam. 16. 6. concerning Dauid &amp; Shemei: when Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid went downe, the winde and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple encreaſed with Abſalom, then indeed Shemei cared not for Dauid, but railed on him, and curſt him, &amp; caſt ſtones at him: Dauid preuailed againſt Abſalom, then he haſts to Dauid with his thouſand peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, trembled and quaked before him, O ſaith he, let not my Lord impute wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto me, I knowe that I haue done amiſſe, I know that I haue offended, &amp;c. ſo truely if God had not an ouerruling hand, if he were not able to recompence euill to his aduerſaries, then there were ſome reaſon that we ſhould be ſecure and careleſſe of his maieſtie; but ſince his might is ſo boundleſſe, that it reacheth from heauen to the earth, from the earth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20608:18"/> to the loweſt hel, ſo as hee is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the mightieſt euen with the breath of his noſthrils, oh therefore let vs hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues before his Maieſtie, let vs cry out with the poore Publican, Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner, Luk. 18. 9. or with the prodigall ſonne, Father, I haue ſinned againſt heauen, and againſt thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne, Luk. 15. 21. let vs cry out with Paul, O wretched man that I am, who ſhal deliuer me from this body of death? Act. 7. 24. let vs with the Nineuits flie to God, with prayer and faſting, Ion. 3. 5. let vs with Manaſſeh, humble our ſelues greatly before God, 2. Chr. 33. 12. with Daniel, confeſſe our ſinnes, and ſeek the Lord, Dan. 9. 3. with Peter, let vs weepe bitterly, Matth. 26. 75. let teares runne downe our cheeks like a riuer, let vs take no reſt, neither let the apple of our eyes ceaſe, Lam. 2. 18. vntill wee haue recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the fauour of God, and found reſt to our ſoules, Mat. 11. 29. What man dares preſume to mooue the wrath of a King? The wrath of a King is as the meſſengers of death, Prou. 16. 14. or as the roaring of a lyon, Prou. 20. 2. Indeede there are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20608:19"/> many court claw-backs and Paraſites, to humour and flatter a king, to crie out vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery occaſion, as Herods auditors did, The voice of God and not of man, Act. 12. 22. ready to bowe to him and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him like a God: but who dares come to him, as Eliiah did to Ahab, and confront him to his face, 2. King. 18. 1. and how then ſhould we dare to offend the king of kings, whoſe lordſhip is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and earth, and ſea, and hel: for hee filleth all places, Ier. 23. 24. the landlord of the whole world, the God of gods, &amp; Lord of lords, Iſa. 41. 2. whoſe face is as a flame of fire, his voice as the roaring of many waters, that hath charets innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and rides vpon the wings of the wind, that meaſures the waters in his fiſt, that compts heauen with his ſpan, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the duſt of the earth in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and weighs the mountaines in a weight, and the hils in a ballance, Iſa. 40. 12. If we dare not offend a King whoſe breath is in his noſthrils, that ſhall die like a man, nay if he do wickedly ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like a beaſt, Pſal. 49. 12. &amp; be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the burning Topheth, which is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the king, Iſa 30. how then ſhould
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20608:19"/> wee dare to ſinne againſt the almightie God of heauen and earth, which hath his way in the whirlwind, that as it was ſaid of the monſter Leuiathan, eſteems iron as ſtraw, and braſſe as rotten wood, Iob 41. 18. that puts his hands to the rocks, and ouerthrowes the mountains, Iob 28. 9. Before whom the earth trembles, and the mountaines melt, Iudg. 5. 5. Oh let vs caſt our ſelues downe before this God, for hee is a great God, and a great king aboue all gods. This of the firſt vſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This doctrine of Gods omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <note place="margin">The 2. vſe fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſolation to the godl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> may ſerue for the comfort of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: for ſince God rules all things, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may be aſſured, that none of all Gods creatures ſhal hurt them: what ſaith the ſpirit of God, concerning the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; they ſhall laugh at deſtruction, and death, and ſhall not be afraid of the beaſt of the earth: The ſtones of the field ſhall be in league with them, and the beaſt of the field ſhall be in league with him, Iob. 5. 22.</p>
               <p>Firſt, God rules in heauen: this may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter <note place="margin">In heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> infinite comfort. For by this they may be aſſured, that none of all Gods creatures in heauen ſhall hurt them. The
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20608:20"/> winde ſhall not blow vpon them, nor a cloud ſhall not riſe but for their good, a droppe of raine falls nor, ſtormes nor winds nor lightnings happen not but by the appointment of God, and therefore hee is ſaid to make the chambers in his clouds, and to ride vpon the wings of the winde, and to breake the bottles of raine, Iob. 38. 38. to haue his treaſures of haile, and his treaſares of ſnow, Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. 22. He cauſes the ſweete influences of the Pley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades, and looſes the bands of Orion, he brings forth Mazaroth in their time, and guides Arcturus with his ſonnes, Iob. 38. 32. If then (as it is ſaid in an higher ſenſe) if God be on our ſide, who can be againſt vs? ſo if God the generall of the armie be on our ſide, which of all his creatures can be againſt vs? no, if he be with vs, he ſhall open his treaſures of ſnow, he ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand his clouds to poure down their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt raine, and their latter raine, and the graſſe ſhall grow vpon the mountaines, Pſal. 147. 8. the elementarie regions the ſtarres, and the planets, ſhal fight for vs: The Sunne ſhall ſtand ſtil in Gibeon, and the moone in the valley of Aylon, Ioſh. 10. 12. the ſunne and moone ſtood ſtill
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20608:20"/> at the prayer of Ioſhua, the ſunne in Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beon and the moone in the vally of Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon; the ſunne ſhall forſake her wonted race, and the moone ſhall ceaſe from her courſe, for the good and benefit of Gods Church &amp; people. Nay, the Angels Gods domeſticall ſeruants, in the check roule, that weare Gods liuerie after a ſpeciall manner, theſe ſhal attend vpon the elect. The Angels of the Lord pitch round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them that feare him, and deliuereth them, Pſal. 34. 7. and the writer to the Hebrewes, Are they not all miniſtring ſpirits, ſent foorth to miniſter for their ſakes, which are heires of ſaluation, Heb. 1. 14. nay, they are not only guarded by Angels, but by armies of angels: an hoaſt of Angels met with Iacob, Gen. 32. 2. &amp; an army of Angels with chariots of fire were ready to protect Eliſha, 2. King. 6. 17. an Angel were ſufficient to protect the whole Church: one army might be ſufficient, but not one angel, not one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but legions, millions, and mirriads of heauenly ſouldiers, pitch their tents, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout euery one that feares the Lord. May we not ſay of this doctrine, as was ſaid of Goliah his ſword, there is none to it: this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20608:21"/> this, is a machleſſe doctrine for a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirit: fal in with God, and make thy peace with him, and not only his other creatures, but euen Archangels, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhall guard thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God ruleth the earth, and therfore <note place="margin">In earth.</note> this may adminiſter further comfort. God raiſeth vp ſtates, &amp; he caſteth down ſtates, for the Lord is Iudge, Pſal. 75. 7. It matters not then how grieuous thy diſtreſſes be, nor how many thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be, for the Lord can raiſe the poore out of the duſt, and the needie out of the doung, that hee may ſet them with the Princes, euen with the Princes of the people. Pſal. 113. 7. That child that hath a wealthy, and powerfull, and potent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, feares neither pouertie nor enemies: and what need we then that haue the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Iehouah for our Lord and father, that lookes downe with vs or againſt vs, Pſal. 33. 12. and binds all his other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their good-abearing, Hoſ. 2. 21. what need we feare ſo long as God rules the earth: Let God take in with Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not a band of Philiſtines can preuaile againſt him: nay Samſon without ſword, or ſpeare, (when the ſpirit of the Lord
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20608:21"/> came vpon him) he ſlew a thouſand men with the iawbone of an aſſe, Iud. 15. 15. Gideons three hundred men, ſhal (with the knocking of potſheards) chaſe their enemies that lie as thick vpon the ground as graſhoppers, Iudg. 7. 22. Ionathan and his armour bearer ſhall terrifie an hoaſt, 1. Sam. 14. 15. little Dauid, with a ſling and ſtone, ſhal vanquiſh mighty Goliah that was harniſed with an helmet of bras 1. Sam. 17. 5. and had boots of braſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his legges, and a ſheild of braſſe vpon his ſhoulders, v. 6. If the Lord be with Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Eſau ſhall haue no power to bid him battell, Gen. 34. 4. If the Lord be with Abraham, Pharaoh his cruell enemie ſhal enrich him, Gen. 22. 19. Thus doth the Lord, order all things for the good of his people: hee makes their enemies their freinds, and deliuers them in battell from the power of the ſword, Iob. 5. 20. God is my ſhepheard, ſaith Dauid, and how can I want? Pſal. 23. how can hee want that hath God for his ſhephard: lift vp thine eyes, ſaid the Lord to Abraham, Eaſtward, Weſtward, Northward, and Southward, all the land that thou ſeeſt wil I giue thee, Gen. 13. 14. Gods wealth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20608:22"/> is not in the Eaſt only, or the Weſt only, but Eaſtward, Weſtward, Northward, &amp; Southward: and therfore no good thing can be wanting to thoſe that feare God: Pſal. 34. If you keepe my Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (it was the Lords promiſe to the Iewes) I will ſend you raine in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the land ſhal yeeld her increaſe, and the trees of the field ſhall giue their fruite, your threſhing ſhall reach vnto the vintage, and your vintage to the ſowing time, and you ſhal eat your bread in plenty, and dwell in your land ſafely, you ſhall chaſe your enemies, and they ſhal fall before you vpon the ſword: fiue of you ſhal chaſe an hundred, &amp; an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſhal put fiue thouſand to flight: Leu 26. 4. 5. 6. In the name of God, and feare of God, let vs conſider this point: doe thine enemies riſe vp againſt thee? and thine adverſaris encreaſe, Pſ. 3. 1. as God ſaid to Abraham, feare not Abraham, I am thy buckler, Gen. 15. 1. ſo ſay I, feare nothing, God is thy buckler: be thine enemies neuer ſo malicious, God that is greater then thine enemies, he ſhall cauſe thoſe that riſe againſt thee, to fall before thy face. If they come againſt thee one
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20608:22"/> way, they ſhall flie before thee ſeauen wayes, Deu. 28. 7. Yea, doth their malice reach to blood; do they lead thee before Kings and Rulers for Chriſt his ſake? ſtill truſt in God, that God that deliuered Daniel out of the lions iaws, preſerued Shadrach, Meſhack, &amp; Abednego amidſt the fierie fornace, that deliuered the children of Iſrael with an high hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pharaoh king of Egypt, Exod. 14. 8. this God is able to preſerue thee in ſpight of thine adverſaries: and hee hath ſaid it, that hee will neuer forget thee. Iſa. 49. 15. If the Lord ſuſtaine thee, what needeſt thou be affraid of ten thouſand people though they ſhould beſet thee round about, Pſalm. 3. 6. Againe, for the things of this life, how canſt thou want, ſince God ruleth the earth. That God that gaue riches, and treaſures, and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours to Salomon, ſo as he gaue gold and ſiluer as ſtones, 2. Chron. 1. 15. That God that choſe Dauid from a ſheepfold to a kingdome, Pſal. 78. 70. this God is able to ſupply thy wants, &amp; he hath promiſe to make thee plentifull in goods, Deut. 28. 11. Let vs ſeriouſly conſider this point: when thine enemies riſe vp againſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20608:23"/> thee, thinke of Gods power: when the world frownes vpon thee, thinke of Gods power: when the ſtreames of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction overwhelme thy ſoule, thinke of Gods power: nay reſolue with Iob, though hee ſhould ſlay mee, yet will I truſt in him, Iob. 13. 15. no queſtion the thought of it ſhal be as comfortable vnto thee, as the coole water to the weary paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, Prov. 25. 25.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to proceed to further matter of comfort: God ruleth the ſea, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">In the ſea.</note> the child of God ſhall be ſafe as well by ſea as by land: no place is more full of perrill and daunger then the ſea, daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for pirats, daungerous for ſtormes, daungerous for rocks, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there doth the Lord mightily vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his people, euen amidſt the billows and ſtormes of the ſea. Excellent for this purpoſe is that in the 107. Pſalm. 2. 3. 4. when the ſtormes riſe, and lift vp the waues of the ſea, when they mount vp to the heauens, and deſcend to the deep, ſo as their ſouls melt for trouble, when they are toſt to &amp; fro like a drunken man, and all their cunning is gone, &amp;c. when thoſe that are vpon the ſea, are in this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20608:23"/> feare &amp; perplexitie, ready to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſeas, to be ſwallowed vp in the ſands, and to daſh againſt the rockes: when the winds whiſtle, &amp; the ſea roars, and ſwells, and darkenes ouerſpreads al: when euery one is at his wits end with aſtoniſhment, why then ſaith Dauid in the ſame Pſalme, they cry vnto God in their trouble, and he brings them out of their diſtreſſe, hee turnes the ſtorme into a calm, ſo as the waues of the ſea are ſtil, and they come to their deſired hauen, v. 30. Thus you ſee, ſea and land, euery place is a place of Sanctuary, of reſt, and refuge, to the righteous man, according to that, Deut. 8. 3. thou ſhalt be bleſſed in the city, and bleſſed in the field: or that in the Pſalmiſt, bleſſed in thy going out, &amp; comming in, Pſ. 121. 8. Lo ſurely thus ſhall the man be bleſſed, that feareth the Lord, Pſal. 128. 4. abroad, at home, by ſea and by land. Thus God dealt by the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, when they trauailed by land: he guides them when they came to the ſea: he diuided the red ſea, and ledde them through it, Pſal. 78. 13. when they did trauell in the day time, he led them with a cloud, and when they went in the night
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20608:24"/> he led them with a pillar of fire, v. 14. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were thirſtie, hee gaue them water out of the hard rocke, v. 16. When they were hungrie, he ſent them Manna from heauen, and rained downe fleſh vpon them like duſt, verſ. 27. Thus the Lord dwels with his ſeruants, Ioh. 14. and not only ſo, but he followes them whereſoe-they goe. Ioſ. 1. 9. The Lord is their kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the Lord is their ſhaddow at their right hand, ſo as the ſunne ſhal not ſmite them by day, nor the moone by night. Pſal. 121. 5. 6. 7.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, God rules the deepes, therfore <note place="margin">In the deeps</note> ſhall hee likewiſe curbe the freſh waters, that they ſhal not ouerflow thee, Iob. 21. 11. Let Siſera oppoſe himſelfe againſt the Church, and the riuer Kiſhon ſhall ſweepe away Siſera, that auncient riuer the riuer Kiſhon, Iud. 5. 21. And the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Marah, though neuer ſo bitter, yet at the prayer of Moſes ſhal the waters of Marah be made ſweete to the Iſraelites, Exod. 15. 25. Nay they ſhall but only drinke of the waters of Marah, no let Moſes ſmite on the rock Horeb, and the waters of Maſſah and Meriboth ſhall flow forth like a riuer, Pſ. 105. 41. Is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20608:24"/> the Aſſyrian a leprous, the riuer Iordan ſhall cure him, 2. King. 5. 15. Are the waters of Iericho neuer ſo deadly; the Prophet Eliſha ſhall heale them for euer: 2. King. 21. 12. And are the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their ſinnes neuer ſo much viſited, with the common plagues of floods, and ouerflowings, and invndations, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we may ſtil ſay of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, as Dauid in another ſenſe. Surely, in the floods of many waters they ſhall not come neere him. Pſalm. 32. 6. Thus heauen, and earth, and ſea, and deepes, are attendants vpon the Saints. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a greater comfort then any of theſe, God is the God of heauen, and therefore euery Chriſtian ſoule may be certenly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of his owne ſaluation: for there can be no condemnation to thoſe which are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, Rom. 8. 1. This then is the bleſſed eſtate of a righteous man, the angels pitch their tents about them here, and they ſhall liue an angels life after death, Matth. 22. 30. The ſunne ſhall not hurt them in the day time, nor the moone by night, &amp; after death they ſhall ſhine like the ſunne, in the glory of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20608:25"/> the father, the ſtars and the planets ſhall fight for them in their courſes, and after death they ſhall glitter like the ſtarrs for euer, Dan. 12. 3. God hath ſpoken it in his word, God that is able to performe his promiſe, Rom. 4. 21. And I am verily perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any thing ſhal be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus, Rom. 8. 38. 39. God hath promiſed it, he that neuer promiſed more then he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to performe, nor neuer performed leſſe then he promiſed: I ſaith Chriſt, giue eternall life to my ſheep, and they ſhall neuer periſh, and none ſhall pluck them out of my hands: for my father that gaue them is greater then any, and no man is able to pluck the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of my fathers hand, Ioh. 10. 29. Chriſt reaſons here from the omnipotency, &amp; mighty power of God, ſo boundleſſe, and infinite, and endleſſe, that thoſe which repoſe their confidence in him, need neuer be afraid. If God giue eternall life to his ſheepe, who is able to take them out of his hand? If God write
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20608:25"/> our names in the booke of life, who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to raze them out againe? if he iuſtifie who can condemne? Rom. 8. 34. if God be on our ſide, who ſhall dare to lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? no I am verily perſwaded, that neither prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallities nor powers, neither Belzebub, nor Belial, nor all the deuills in hell, ſhall be able to ſeperate vs from the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus. The deuil may goe about like a roaring Lion, ſeeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure: but God hath the Deuill in a chaine, and greater is hee, that is in vs, then hee which is in the world. Ioh. 4. 4. Truſt in God, and the gates of hell, ſhall neuer bee able to preuaile againſt vs. Matth. 16. 18.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
